{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Early objects created using this device are called incunabula. This device was introduced to\nVenice by Aldus Manutius and brought to England by William Caxton. A goldsmith from Mainz\nused a screw-press for his \"movable-type\" version of this device. For 10 points, name this device\nfirst created in the West by Johannes Gutenberg.",
      "answer": "printing press"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1861, Johann Reis arguably accomplished this task by making use of magneto-restriction.\nElisha Gray claimed to have accomplished this task, though he lost out on a patent to the man\nwho is generally credited with this accomplishment and used the result to transmit, \"Watson,\ncome here, I want you.\" For 10 points, name this achievement of Alexander Graham Bell.",
      "answer": [
        "inventing the telephone",
        "telephone"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Zacharias Janssen may have invented the first version of this device, which was first used in\nbiology by Anton van Leeuwenhoek (pr. LAY-ven-hoke). In 1932, Ernst Ruska pioneered the\n\"electron\" type of this device, which was used to discover cells in cork by Robert Hooke. For 10\npoints, identify this device which lens-grinders created to peer at tiny objects.",
      "answer": "microscope"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man's visit to the Keeling Islands inspired his book The Structure and Distribution of\nCoral Reefs. As part of that same trip with Robert FitzRoy, he noticed that different finches on\nthe Galapagos Islands occupied different niches. For 10 points, name this man whose time on the\nBeagle inspired him to introduce the theory of evolution by natural selection.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles Darwin",
        "Darwin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Emmanuel Timoni first described a method of preventing this disease, which Mary Worley\nMontagu famously was guarded against in Constantinople. Cotton Mather wrote in support of\ninoculation against this disease, which was proved feasible in England by Edward Jenner. For 10\npoints, name this formerly devastating disease which was eliminated by the 1990s.",
      "answer": "smallpox"
    },
    {
      "question": "Charles Redheffer's exhibition of one of these devices was undone by a precocious child who\nnoticed the wearing of gear teeth. John Gamgee's attempt to create a device of this kind called\nthe Zeromotor failed because of the energy needed to cool ammonia. For 10 points, name these\npseudoscientific devices which were proved impossible by the Second Law of Thermodynamics.",
      "answer": [
        "perpetual motion machines",
        "perpetual motion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Schoolgirl Venetia Burney proposed what is now the official name of this object. This body\nwas discovered in 1930 using the blink comparator machine by Vesto Slipher's new apprentice,\nClyde Tombaugh. In 2006, this object was demoted by the International Astronomical Union to\n\"dwarf planet\" status. For 10 points, name this trans-Neptunian object and former ninth planet.",
      "answer": "Pluto"
    },
    {
      "question": "Peter Shann Ford has attempted to prove, using acoustic analysis, that this man did not flub a\nline that had been scripted for him. This man indicated that \"the Eagle has landed\" while on a\nmission with Michael Collins and Buzz Aldrin. For 10 points, name this commander of Apollo\n11 who said \"one small step for man, one giant leap for mankind\" as he took the first step onto\nthe Moon.",
      "answer": [
        "Neil Armstrong",
        "Armstrong"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The rVSV-ZEBOV vaccine has been shown effective in treating this disease. Emile Ouamouno died six\ndays after contracting this disease, and Eric Duncan infected two Americans with it. Liberia was declared\nfree of this disease after 42 days with no new cases. For ten points, name this disease which caused a 2014\nepidemic in West Africa.",
      "answer": [
        "Ebola virus disease",
        "Ebola",
        "Ebola hemorrhagic fever"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This thinker’s work The Sand Reckoner is the most comprehensive surviving source for Aristarchus’\nheliocentric theory. He was the first to develop formulas for the volume and surface area of a sphere and\ninvented a namesake “screw” used for raising water, but his “death ray” did not actually sink a fleet\nattacking his home, Syracuse. For ten points, name this scientist who supposedly ran through the streets\nshouting “Eureka!” after discovering the principle of buoyancy.",
      "answer": [
        "Archimedes of Syracuse",
        "Archimedes"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist beat Emile Berliner to the patent of the carbon transmitter and is attributed with\ncreating the world’s first industrial research and development lab, found in West Orange, New Jersey. The\nquote “genius is 1 percent inspiration and 99 percent perspiration” is attributed to this Wizard of Menlo\nPark. For ten points, name this prolific inventor of the phonograph, movie camera, and incandescent light\nbulb.",
      "answer": [
        "Thomas Edison",
        "Edison"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Michael Servetus believed that the soul could be found in this body system and was the first to\ncorrectly describe its function in the lungs. Marcello Malpighi confirmed a hypothesis about this system\nmade by a 17th century English physician about how two major components were connected. Robert\nJarvik developed a replacement for the major organ of this system, which was studied by Galen and\nWilliam Harvey. For ten points, name this body system consisting of the heart, blood, and blood vessels.",
      "answer": [
        "circulatory system",
        "cardiovascular system",
        "circulatory",
        "cardiovascular"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Rafael Bombelli is regarded as the “inventor” of these numbers, since he developed the rules for their\narithmetic operations. It is useful to color-code graphs of functions that contain these numbers, since\nthose graphs have four dimensions. Euler’s formula equates “e to the i theta” to a number of this type.\nFor ten points, give this type of number that has both real and imaginary components.",
      "answer": [
        "complex numbers",
        "complex"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This crisis unites the storytellers of The Decameron, who try to escape it in Florence. This event\nspread as far as Iceland, supposedly carried by fleas on rats. This disease, caused by the pathogen Yersinia\npestis, was named for large swellings of the lymph nodes called buboes. For ten points, name this disease\nthat swept through much of Asia and Europe during the 14th century, killing tens of millions of people.",
      "answer": [
        "Black Death",
        "Black Plague",
        "Bubonic Plague"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This action has been successfully completed at Fra Mauro and the Ocean of Storms. The inability\nof the Zond program to finish a successful mission doomed Soviet efforts to even attempt this action. A\nspeech delivered at Rice University in 1962 claimed that America chooses to do this “and do the other\nthings not because they are easy, but because they are hard.” For ten points, name this accomplishment\nachieved by 12 Americans, first performed in 1969 by Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong during Apollo 11.",
      "answer": [
        "landing on the Moon",
        "land on the Moon",
        "Moon landing",
        "sending peopel to the Moon",
        "going to the Moon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Daniel Dennett wrote a book titled for this man’s “Dangerous Idea.” Some of this man’s work was jointly published with Alfred Russel Wallace. His work was defended by the “Bulldog” Thomas Huxley as superior to the similar theories proposed by Lamarck. This man described his journey to the Galapagos Islands in 1839’s The Voyage of the Beagle. For ten points, name this British scientist whose On the Origin of Species is considered the cornerstone of evolutionary biology.",
      "answer": [
        "Charles Darwin",
        "Darwin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Paul Rothemund of Caltech initiated the practice of using this material for origami. Its function was\ndemonstrated through the use of sulfur and phosphorous to label bacteriophages in a 1952 experiment\nperformed by Hershey and Chase. This molecule’s structure was determined with the aid of X-ray\ndiffraction images taken by Rosalind Franklin. For ten points, name this molecule whose double-helix\nstructure was determined by Watson and Crick and that carries our genetic code.",
      "answer": [
        "Deoxyribonucleic acid",
        "DNA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A virus capable of causing this disease was discovered in 1911 by Peyton Rous. The fusion gene\nBCR-ABL1, found on the Philadelphia chromosome, causes a tyrosine kinase to always be on, leading to a\ntype of this disease. It is protected against by the protein p53, the “guardian of the genome.” Metastasis\nis the spread of, for ten points, what type of disease, including lymphomas and leukemia, that leads to\nuncontrolled cell growth and the formation of tumors?",
      "answer": [
        "cancer",
        "sarcoma"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man stuck a needle in his own eye during his studies on light and color, which he published in\nOpticks. This man feuded with Gottfried Leibniz over credit for the invention of calculus, a system of\nmath that inspired, but was not proven in, this man’s Principia Mathematica. For ten points, name this\nEnglish scientist who developed the law of universal gravitation and the three laws of motion.",
      "answer": [
        "Sir Isaac Newton",
        "Newton",
        "Isaac Newton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) What Polish astronomer developed a heliocentric model, leading to a “Revolution” in\nastronomy named for him?",
      "answer": [
        "Nicolas Copernicus",
        "Copernicus",
        "Copernican",
        "Copernican model",
        "Copernican theory",
        "Copernican revolution"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This product was named by Rowland Hanson, who shot down the proposed name \"Interface\nManager.\" In 1992, this product's manufacturer decided to focus on it and stop developing OS/2.\nThis product's popular versions included 3.1, NT, and 95, prior to the release of version 7 in\n2009. For 10 points, name this operating system produced by Microsoft.",
        "answer": "Windows"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "OS/2 was a joint project of Microsoft and what former titan of the industry, known as\n\"Big Blue\" for the color of both its logo and its once-mandatory employee ties?",
        "answer": "IBM"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The \"foundations\" of this field were described in a book by David Hilbert, and its \"hyperbolic\"\nform was pioneered by János Bolyai (pr. YAH-nowsh BOWL-yai) and the Russian Nikolai\nLobachevsky (pr. LOH-buh-CHEFF-skee). For 10 points, name this math field whose\nfoundational text is the Elements by Euclid (pr. YOOK-lid), which discusses the parallel\npostulate and Pythagorean theorem.",
        "answer": "geometry"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other kind of mathematics was invented simultaneously by Gottfried Leibniz and\nIsaac Newton, who long quarreled over the credit for its discovery?",
        "answer": "calculus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "William Jopling wrote the standard textbook on this disease. The Greek island of Spinalonga\nonce housed people with this disease, who were treated by Marianne Cope and \"Father Damien\"\non Molokai in Hawaii. For 10 points, name this disease whose causative agent was identified in\n1873 by Gerhard Hansen, and whose sufferers were once isolated into namesake \"colonies.\"",
        "answer": "leprosy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1950, William Jopling established a leprosy hospital named after what body of water\nin the Middle East, in which lepers were instructed to bathe in the Bible?",
        "answer": [
          "Jordan River",
          "Jordan"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Bahcall and Raymond Davis searched for these particles in the Homestake experiment.\nThe 1956 experiment of Clyde Cowan and Frederick Reines confirmed their existence. Enrico\nFermi coined the name for these particles, whose \"flavor oscillation\" was a problem of late\ntwentieth-century physics. For 10 points, name these particles with very little mass and no charge.",
        "answer": [
          "neutrinos",
          "antineutrinos",
          "solar neutrinos"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The neutrino was first proposed, though without a name, by what scientist, whose\nconcept of particle spin led him to formulate a namesake \"exclusion principle\" about fermions?",
        "answer": [
          "Wolfgang Pauli",
          "Pauli"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Jacob Bernoulli discovered that this number is the \"force of interest,\" the limit of the interest\naccruable on a dollar by increasing the frequency of compounding. A 1727 paper on the\nexplosive force of cannons introduced this number as the base of the natural logarithm. For 10\npoints, identify this mathematical constant named for its Swiss popularizer.",
        "answer": [
          "e",
          "Euler's number",
          "Euler's constant"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Euler (pr. OY-ler) also established graph theory in an attempt to solve the problem\ninvolving seven of what kind of structure in Königsberg?",
        "answer": [
          "bridges"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Biologist George Gaylord Simpson was a vehement opponent of this theory. Frank Taylor first\nproposed this theory in 1908, based on observing similarities in distant mountain ranges. This\ntheory was picked up in 1912 by Alfred Wegener, who popularized it. For 10 points, identify this\ntheory, ancestral to plate tectonics, which states that large land masses move over time.",
        "answer": "continental drift"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Wegener proposed that the continents could be fit together to form an \"Urkontinent,\" a\nprehistoric land mass now known by what Greek-derived name?",
        "answer": "Pangaea"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1850, a seeming discrepancy in this scientist’s work was resolved by Stanislao Cannizzaro.\nThis man’s breakthrough was realizing the distinction between atoms and molecules in a gas,\ncausing this veteran of the Piedmont uprising to be the namesake of the number 6.022 times 10\nto the 23rd. For 10 points, identify this discoverer of the number of particles in a mole.",
        "answer": [
          "Amadeo Avogadro",
          "Avogadro"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Avogadro was the first to correctly determine the chemical formula for what substance,\nwhich was moved against the force of gravity by Archimedes’s Screw?",
        "answer": "water"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This theory was advocated by John Needham due to a faulty experimental design. Lazzaro\nSpallanzani argued against this theory by showing that Needham had failed to entirely seal the\nboiled flask used before observing “animalcules.” For 10 points, name this theory finally put to\nrest by Louis Pasteur, which holds that rotting food directly creates life.",
        "answer": "spontaneous generation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What scientist, the namesake of cells found around nerves, coined the dogma that “all\ncells come from pre-existing cells” following the collapse of spontaneous generation theory?",
        "answer": [
          "Theodor Schwann",
          "Schwann"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1962, Henry Hammond Hess proposed that convection currents within this layer are the\ncause of seafloor spreading. In 1909, the boundary atop this layer was discovered by Andrija\nMohorovicíc (AHN-ree-huh moh-hoh-ROH-veech-itch). For 10 points, name this layer of the\nEarth which was hypothesized in the nineteenth century to lie between the core and crust.",
        "answer": "mantle"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1972, J. Tuzo Wilson proposed that mantle “hot spots” were responsible for the\nformation of what island chain, which was unified under King Kamehameha I?",
        "answer": [
          "Hawaiian islands",
          "Hawaii"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Two important models of this kind of device were introduced in 1976, Chuck Peddle’s 6502\nand Zilog’s Z80. Those devices competed with the widely used 8080, from the company which\nmanufactured influential later models of these devices such as the x86, Pentium series, and i7.\nFor 10 points, name these devices at the heart of a computer, which are made by Intel.",
        "answer": [
          "microprocessors",
          "processors",
          "CPUs",
          "central processing units"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "From 1991 to 2005, what company used RISC-based PowerPC processors almost\nexclusively, such as in machines that ran its iconic System 7?",
        "answer": [
          "Apple Inc.",
          "Apple",
          "Apple Computer Inc."
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This object was excommunicated by Calixtus III, who believed it boded evil for the defenders of\nBelgrade. Mark Twain said that this object and he were “two unaccountable freaks” and claimed that he\nwould “go out with it,” a prediction that came true when he died in 1910. The Giotto Probe flew through\nthe coma of this object in 1986, which will be visible again in 2061. For ten points, name this comet that\napproaches Earth roughly every 76 years.",
        "answer": [
          "Halley’s comet",
          "Halley",
          "1P/Halley"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1910, Earth passed through this feature of Halley’s comet, leading some to buy gas masks in\nfear that Earth’s atmosphere would be poisoned.",
        "answer": "the tail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following the acceptance of this theory, Koch’s Postulates were developed. Girolamo Fracastoro was\nthe first to propose this theory, which Francesco Redi supported by observing 3 jars of meatloaf and eggs\nover time. The discrediting of spontaneous generation finally led to the widespread acceptance of this\ntheory. For ten points, Galen’s miasma theory was replaced by what theory that diseases are caused by\nmicroscopic organisms like viruses and bacteria?",
        "answer": [
          "germ theory of disease",
          "germ"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Spontaneous generation was disproven by this French microbiologist who also discovered that\nheating beer killed harmful bacteria.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis Pasteur",
          "Pasteur"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An exterior part of this planet named for John Couch Adams has subdivisions called Fraternite,\nEgalite, and Liberte. In 1989, large storms on this planet were discovered by Voyager 2 and were named \nScooter and the Great Dark Spot. Urbain Le Verrier was able to mathematically predict this planet’s\nexistence by studying the orbit of a neighbor planet. For ten points, name this planet with a methane-blue\natmosphere that, after the demotion of Pluto, became the furthest planet of the Solar System.",
        "answer": "Neptune"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Le Verrier mathematically predicted Neptune’s existence by studying the orbit of this seventh\nplanet from the Sun.",
        "answer": "Uranus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After one of these events, Harry Fielding Reid developed his elastic-rebound theory. In the 1930s,\ntwo Caltech scientists were inspired by the apparent magnitude scale of stars to develop a system for\nmeasuring these events. That scale has been replaced by the Moment Magnitude scale. The Mercalli\nintensity scale measures the destruction caused by these events. The Richter scale also measures, for ten\npoints, what seismic events that cause massive shaking of the ground?",
        "answer": "earthquakes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Earthquake intensity scales are logarithmic, as is this standard scale for measuring the intensity\nof sound. This system’s unit is named for a Scottish inventor.",
        "answer": [
          "decibel system",
          "bel",
          "decibel scale"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man succeeded Isaac Barrow and served 33 years as Lucasian Professor of Mathematics in\nCambridge. His treatise Opticks introduced the corpuscular theory of light. This physicist laid the\nframework for classical mechanics in his three-volume Principia Mathematica, and he feuded with\nGottfried Leibniz over credit for the invention of calculus. For ten points, name this British physicist and\nmathematician who devised three laws of motion.",
        "answer": [
          "Sir Isaac Newton",
          "Newton"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In possible reference to the short stature of his rival, Robert Hooke, Newton claimed that if he\nhad “seen further,” it was by standing on this metaphorical concept.",
        "answer": "the shoulders of giants"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Citizens of this country, including Arthur Rudolph, were brought to the United States in Operation\nPaperclip. This country’s scientists developed a liquid-propellant engine for use in the first man-made\nobject to cross the Karman line into outer space; that object was used a “vengeance weapon” in 1944. For\nten points, name this country whose rocket scientists, including Werner Von Braun, developed the V-2\nrocket but did not create a nuclear weapon before it lost World War II.",
        "answer": [
          "Nazi Germany",
          "Germany",
          "Third Reich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Operation Paperclip hid the Nazi backgrounds of the imported scientists, including Hubertus\nStrughold. Strughold had used human test subjects in his work at this German concentration camp near\nMunich, which the Americans used as a military base after the war.",
        "answer": "Dachau"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist described the “chemistry of the imponderable” in a Nobel Prize lecture explaining the\nwork of Henri Becquerel. This scientist co-authored a study comparing tumor cell and healthy cell death\nrates when exposed to an element that this chemist isolated in 1910, four years after the death of her\nhusband Pierre. The first woman to win a Nobel Prize was, for ten points, what Polish-French physicist\nwho discovered radium while studying radioactive decay?",
        "answer": [
          "Marie Sklodowska Curie",
          "Marie Curie",
          "Marie Sklodowska",
          "Sklodowska",
          "Curie"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marie Curie isolated radium from a sample of radium chloride via a cathode of this element;\nthe radium reacted with this element to form an amalgam. This element, which is a liquid at room\ntemperature, has largely been phased out of use in scientific thermometers.",
        "answer": [
          "mercury",
          "Hg"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "AVIATION",
      "prompt": "In the history of human flight, who or what...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the last name of Orville and Wilbur, the builders of the first successful airplane?",
          "answer": [
            "Wright",
            "Wright Brothers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first woman to fly solo non-stop across the Atlantic in 1932, but disappeared in the Pacific\nfive years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Amelia Earhart",
            "Earhart"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nickname of German WWI ace Manfred von Richthofen?",
          "answer": "The Red Baron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first pilot to break the sound barrier?",
          "answer": [
            "Chuck Yeager",
            "Yeager"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the type of aircraft invented by the Montgolfier [mohn-GOAL-fee-ay] brothers in 1783?",
          "answer": "hot air balloon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the airplane that Charles Lindbergh flew for the first solo non-stop trans-Atlantic flight?",
          "answer": "The Spirit of St. Louis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Russian designer of the R-4 helicopter?",
          "answer": [
            "Igor Sikorsky",
            "Sikorsky"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nickname of the H-4 Hercules, a flying boat designed by Howard Hughes?",
          "answer": "Spruce Goose"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man published regular weather data in his Meteorological Observations. As he was\nless influential in his own time than Jakob Berzelius, it was Berzelius's endorsement which\nled to acceptance of his ideas. He was the first to state what is now called (20 pts) ",
        "Charles's Law\nand form a theory about red-green colorblindness, as well as the law of (10 pts) ",
        "partial pressures.\nFor 10 points, name this early nineteenth century British scientist who popularized the modern\nidea of atoms."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "John Dalton",
        "Dalton"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These things were first discovered using Charles Chamberlain's porcelain filters. By\n1910, Peyton Rous demonstrated their role in cancers. In 1892, Dmitri Ivanovsky\ndemonstrated that these things caused the (20 pts) ",
        "tobacco mosaic disease. Walter Reed found\nthe first large-scale human consequence of these things, when he showed that one of them\ncauses (*) yellow fever. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, name this quasi-living genetic information vector that is\nnot a bacteria."
      ],
      "answer": "virus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In mid-2014, popular examples of this kind of product included the Moto 360 and Pebble\nSteel. Samsung launched several of these products under the (20 pts) ",
        "\"Gear\" line, and these\nproducts are named for a Sony line that integrates with (10 pts) ",
        "Android operating systems. For\n10 points, Apple caused a stir by announcing the launch of their version of what kind of wearable\ntechnology product, which is often used for fitness monitoring or portable media capabilities?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "smart watches"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Russell S. Penniman found a cheaper way to make this product, which must be periodically rotated to avoid the pooling of its active component out of the (20 pts) ",
        "sawdust medium. This product reduced the danger of using black powder or unmodified (10 pts) ",
        "nitroglycerin, and led to its inventor being dubbed \"the merchant of death.\" For 10 points, identify this explosive with mining and military applications, which requires a blasting cap and was devised by Alfred Nobel."
      ],
      "answer": "dynamite"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Julius von Sachs identified the organelles in which this process takes place. The\nexperiments of Jan Ingenhousz (pr. ING-en-hoos) showed that this process altered the mass\nof the (20 pts) ",
        "organisms involved. Joseph Priestley performed an experiment involving a candle\nand (10 pts) ",
        "mint that showed that this process changes the composition of air. For 10 points, identify\nthis process of plants using light to create sugars from carbon dioxide."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "photosynthesis",
        "Calvin cycle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Alexey Leonov posits that the training crash which killed this man in 1968 was caused by\nan accidental near-miss with another fighter jet. This man, who was selected out of twenty\ncandidates from (20 pts) ",
        "Star City, whistled the patriotic song \"The Motherland Hears\" while\nre-entering the atmosphere aboard (10 pts) ",
        "Vostok 1. For 10 points, name this Soviet cosmonaut\nwho, in 1961, became the first human to leave the Earth's atmosphere."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Yuri Gagarin",
        "Gagarin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tral stations and the Command-Measurement Complex were used to observe this object.\nA part of this vehicle was derived from an R7 intercontinental ballistic missile, and it used (20 pts) ",
        "four radio antennas to broadcast a repeating, pulsing signal. President Eisenhower\ncreated ARPA and the government increased funding for (10 pts) ",
        "science and technology after this\nobject was launched in October 1957. The Soviets started the Space Race with the launch of, for ten\npoints, what first artificial satellite?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sputnik I",
        "Sputnik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Aaron rationed battery power during this event. Ken Mattingly was supposed to\nhave participated in this event but was unable due to (20 pts) ",
        "German Measles, while Fred\nHaise suffered a serious urinary tract infection during it. During this event, the service (10 pts) ",
        "module’s number 2 oxygen tank suffered a failure, causing Jack Swigert and Jim Lovell to report\n“Houston, we’ve had a problem”. For ten points, name this NASA mission whose moon landing was\naborted but which returned safely to Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "Apollo 13"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Beyonce was criticized for insensitivity to this event in her track XO. This event delayed\nthe State of the Union address by a week; instead, President (20 pts) ",
        "Reagan gave a speech\nfrom the Oval Office about a group who “’slipped the surly bonds of earth’ to ‘touch the face\nof God.’” An unusually large number of (10 pts) ",
        "schoolchildren saw the broadcast of this event because\nChrista McAuliffe, a teacher, was aboard the doomed craft. For ten points, name this 1986 disaster in\nwhich a NASA shuttle disintegrated shortly after launch."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Space Shuttle Challenger explosion",
        "Challenger",
        "Challenger explosion"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Theodor Benfey proposed a spiral replacement for this construct. This construct gained\npopularity because its developer left empty spaces for (20 pts) ",
        "predicted, missing members,\nwhich were given prefixes like eka-. Synthesis work by Glenn Seaborg led to a 1945 expansion\nof this construct, adding a row for (10 pts) ",
        "actinides. This construct is organized in an 18-column array,\nprogressing by atomic number. For ten points, name this construct developed by Dmitri Mendeleyev that\ngroups all of the known chemical elements."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "periodic table of the elements",
        "periodic table"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s law is a statement of Georges Lemaˆıtre’s [le-MET’s] observation that distant\ngalaxies are Doppler shifted to indicate movement away from Earth. A mathematical\nformulation of that law involves a (20 pts) ",
        "constant, also named for this man, whose inverse is\napproximately the age of the universe. In 1925, this astronomer used Cepheid [SEH-fee-id]\nvariables to estimate the distance to M31, (10 pts) ",
        "Andromeda, one of numerous nebulae shown to\nactually be galaxies by this man. For ten points, name this American astronomer who was honored as the\nnamesake of a NASA space telescope launched in 1990."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edwin Hubble",
        "Hubble",
        "Hubble Space Telescope"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This mathematician proved the undecidability of the halting problem. A finite set of user\ninstructions, an infinitely long memory tape, and a symbol reader make up a theoretical (20 pts) ",
        "machine conceived by this man; if a problem is computable, that device can solve\nit, according to a hypothesis named for this man and Alonzo Church. A computer that is\nindistinguishable from a human in (10 pts) ",
        "conversation would pass this man’s namesake test. For ten\npoints, name this British computer scientist who helped break the Enigma code during World War II\nbefore being prosecuted for his homosexuality."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Alan Turing",
        "Turing"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Cantilevers are used in the “atomic force” type of these devices, which were inspired by\na scanning, tunnelling type that won the 1986 Physics Nobel. Ernst Ruska and Max Knoll\nworked to develop types of these devices based on raster scattering of (20 pts) ",
        "electrons. In the\n17th century, Anton Van Leeuwenhoek built one of these devices to observe what he called\nanimalcules, organisms that Robert (10 pts) ",
        "Hooke later noted were made up of cells. For ten points,\nname these scientific tools that allow you to see very small things."
      ],
      "answer": "microscope"
    }
  ]
}